Hans Peter Kraus Collection of Spanish American Documents
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Hans Peter Kraus Collection of Spanish American Documents 1433-1966 1500-1800
MSS31013
Kraus, Hans Peter, 1907-1988
300 items
11 containers
4 linear feet
4 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Bookman, collector, and bibliophile. Letters, decrees, order books, reports, instructions, dispatches, printed material, and miscellaneous legal documents concerning the history of colonial Spanish America, including the activities of the Mexican Inquisition.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Aguirre, Lope de, -1561.; Arredondo, Antonio de.; Calderón, Antonio de.; Casas, Bartolomé de las, 1484-1566.; Céspedes Vallejo Diaz, Pedro de.; Gourgues family.; Gourgues, Dominique de, 1530?-1593.; Kraus, Hans Peter, 1907-1988.; Landa, Diego de, 1524-1579.; Mendoza, Antonio de, approximately 1492-1552.; Núñez Cabeza de Vaca, Alvar, active 16th century.; Pereyns, Simón, -1589.; Quiroga y Losada, Diego.; Ursúa, Pedro de, 1526-1561.; Velasco, Luis de, 1500?-1564.; Verrazzano, Giovanni da, 1485-1528.; Vespucci, Amerigo, 1451-1512.; Zumárraga, Juan de, 1468-1548.
Organizations
Catholic Church--Mexico.
Subjects
Indians, Treatment of--New Spain.; Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.--New Spain.; Inquisition--Mexico.; Taxation--New Spain.
Places
America--Discovery and exploration.; Florida--History.; France--Foreign relations--Spain.; Mexico--Politics and government.; New Spain--Politics and government.; North America--History.; Spain--Colonies--America--Economic policy.; Spain--Colonies--America.; Spain--Foreign relations--France.; Spain--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Spain.; United States--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States--History.
Titles
Hans Peter Kraus Collection of Spanish American Documents at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Collectors.
Acquisition Information
The collection of Spanish American documents of Hans Peter Kraus, bookman, collector, and bibliophile, was given to the Library of Congress by Kraus in 1969. An additional item was purchased for the Library by Kraus in 1970.
Additional Guides
Preliminary arrangement and descriptions of the Kraus Collection were prepared for Kraus by Richard Boulind. The collection is also described in Hans P. Kraus Collection of Hispanic American Manuscripts (Washington, D.C.: Library of Congress, 1974) by J. Benedict Warren, available online at https://www.loc.gov/item/74001097/.
Related Material
In addition to the Kraus material, the Manuscript Division holds a collection of colonial Spanish American manuscripts in the Edward Stephen Harkness Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on four reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
The Hans Peter Kraus Collection of Spanish American Documents is available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000116. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the online edition.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of Spanish American documents of Hans Peter Kraus (1907-1988) spans the years 1433 to 1966, with the bulk of the items dated from the sixteenth through the eighteenth centuries. The collection relates to the history and culture of colonial Spanish America, including the early history of territories now part of the United States. Contained in the collection are colonial documents recording the exploration of the New World, the government of New Spain (Mexico), the administration of the Inquisition, taxation and economic conditions in the colonies, Spanish relationships with Native Americans and the French, and the loss of parts of the Spanish empire to American expansion. The collection includes material relating to explorers Amerigo Vespucci (1451-1512), Giovanni da Verrazzano (1485-1528), Alvar Núñez Cabeza de Vaca (16th cent.), Pedro de Ursúa (d.1561), and Lope de Aguirre (d.1561). It also includes letters and documents from the archives of Juan de Zumárraga (1468-1548), bishop of Mexico, and his successors. The collection is in English, Spanish, French, and Italian and is organized in a Spanish American Documents series and a Miscellany series consisting of notes and printed matter providing descriptions and partial translations of the collection. The collection contains letters, decrees, order books, reports, instructions, dispatches, printed material, and miscellaneous legal documents arranged by number as listed in Hans P. Kraus Collection of Hispanic American Manuscripts prepared by J. Benedict Warren.
One of the earliest documents in the collection is a contemporary manuscript copy of Vespucci's letter to Piero Soderini (1452-1522), 10 September 1504, in which he discussed all four of his voyages (item 119). Verrazzano's explorations, including his survey of the eastern seaboard of North America, are documented in letters, documents, and transcripts relating to the explorer and his family (item 121). Contemporary narratives and a copy of a royal dispatch trace the history of Ursúa's and Aguirre's exploratory expedition down the Amazon River and the latter's subsequent mutiny (items 141-143). Three original documents highlight the family life of Núñez Cabeza de Vaca, a pioneer in the conquest of Mexico and the exploration of Florida (item 122). Other material concerning early attempts to colonize Florida and the territories north of Mexico are included in an order book maintained by Viceroy Luis de Velasco (1500?-1564) and his predecessor, Antonio de Mendoza (1492?-1552) (item 140); a volume of documents regarding Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo Diaz, a soldier who served in Florida (item 148); a letter of Diego Quiroga y Losada, governor of Florida (item 152); a treatise by Antonio de Arredondo on Spanish claims to the colony of Georgia; and the letters and documents of the Gourgues family, in particular a narrative manuscript of the expedition of Dominique de Gourgues (1530?-1593) to Florida, 1567-1568 (item 144). Five variant versions of Gourgues's narrative located in the Bibliotheque Nationale, Paris, France (Fonds Français 2145, 3884, 6124, 19899, and 20794) have been reproduced on two reels of microfilm and are available in the Manuscript Division Reading Room. (Microfilm shelf no. 17,674)
A collection of decrees and letters, a majority of which resided in the archives of Zumárraga, relates primarily, though not exclusively, to the Catholic church in New Spain (items 1-116). In addition to ecclesiastical affairs, these items also document the government and administration of Mexico including its social structure and culture, public health, education, the arts, public works, and the living conditions of its native population. The documents bear the signatures of Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor (1500-1558), and his wife, Isabel, Empress (1503-1539), and their son and daughter, Philip II, King of Spain (1527-1598), and Juana de Austria, Princess of Portugal (1535-1573), and their descendants, Philip III (1578-1621) and Philip IV (1605-1665), kings of Spain. Another set of documents concerning the civil administration of New Spain also illuminates the career of Zumárraga's colleague, Bartolomé de las Casas, bishop of Chiapas (items 123-139). These items reflect the development and impact of the New Laws of the Indies, 1542, and the colonists' reaction to them. Items pertaining to the Inquisition in Mexico include documents of the trial of artist Simón Pereyns (fl. 1558-1588) (item 145); material relating to Antonio and Diego Calderón and family, official printers to the Holy Office of the Inquisition (item 149); and a holograph and printed volume of the rules and regulations governing the fraternity of Saint Peter Martyr, a brotherhood consisting of members of the Inquisition (item 151).
Among the latest items in the collection are dispatches sent in 1819 from Mexico to Spain by Juan Ruiz de Apodaca which contain information on the government, condition, and defense of the Spanish territories that are now part of the United States, including Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, and California, with references to American forces and settlements in Louisiana and Florida (item 162).
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in two series:
Spanish American Documents, 1433-1877
Miscellany, 1938-1966
Container List
Microfilm edition available. Shelf no. 14,833
- Spanish American Documents, 1433-1877 (Box 1-10, Reel 1-4)
  Letters, decrees, order books, reports, instructions, dispatches, printed material, and miscellaneous legal documents relating to the history of Spanish America.
  Arranged numerically by the item number recorded in Hans P. Kraus Collection of Hispanic American Manuscripts by J. Benedict Warren.
  - Item nos. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - 1-116, Decrees and letters from the archives of Juan de Zumárraga, 1527-1660
      - 1, Royal cedula to the audencia of the Island of Española
      - 2, Royal cedula to the [Royal Treasury] officials of New Spain
      - 3, Duplicate of a royal cedula to the audencia of New Spain issued in Toledo, August 24, 1529
      - 4, Royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, confirmed bishop-elect of Mexico
      - 5, Royal cedula to the audencia of New Spain
      - 6, Royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop-elect of Mexico
      - 7, Royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, confirmed bishop-elect of Mexico
      - 8, Royal cedula to [Juan de Zumárraga], bishop of Mexico
      - 9, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 10, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 11, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 12, Royal cedula to the audiencia and treasury officials of New Spain
      - 13, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 14, Royal letter to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 15, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 16, Royal letter to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 17, Duplicate of a royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain, issued in Valladolid, December 7, 1537
      - 18, Notarized copy of a royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 19, Notarized copy of a royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain and the bishop of Mexico
      - 19A, Letter to His Imperial Catholic Majesty [Charles I of Spain]
      - 20, Royal letter to the bishops of Mexico, Guatemala, and Antequera [Oaxaca]
      - 21, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 22, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 23, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 24, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 25, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 26, Royal cedula to the provincial of the Franciscan Order in New Spain
      - 27, Royal cedula to the royal [treasury] officials of New Spain
      - 28, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain and to [Juan de Zumárraga], bishop of Mexico
      - 29, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 30, Copy of a royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 31, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 32, Cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 33, Notarized copy of a cedula to the governors of Guatemala, Higueras, and Honduras and other justices in the Spanish Indies
      - 34, Royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 35, Copy of a cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 36, Notarized copy of a royal cedula to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 37, Royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 38, Notarized copy of a royal cedula to Vasco de Quiroga, bishop of Michoacán
      - 39, Royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 40, Royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 41, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 42, Royal cedula to Juan de Zumárraga, bishop of Mexico
      - 43, Notarized copy of a royal cedula to the audiencias of New Spain, Guatemala, and New Galicia
      - 44, Royal cedula to Alonso de Montúfar, archbishop of Mexico
      - 45, Royal letter to Alonso de Montúfar, archbishop of Mexico
      - 46, Royal cedula to the audiencia of Mexico
      - 47, Royal cedula to the audiencia of Mexico
      - 48, Royal cedula to [Alonso de Montúfar], archbishop of Mexico
      - 49, Notarized copy of a power of attorney to Bachiller Juan de la Riba, vicar general of the archdiocese of Mexico, or to his successor, to Juan de Salazar and Francisco Ramírez, attorneys for cases in the audiencia of New Spain, and to Juan Ruiz Rubio, canon of the cathedral of Mexico, and Juan Ortiz de Oribe, the last two of whom were at the royal court
      - 50, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 51, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 52, Royal cedula to [Luis de Velasco], Viceroy of New Spain
      - 53, Royal cedula to [Luis de Velasco], Viceroy of New Spain
      - 54, Copy of a royal cedula to [Alonso de Montúfar], archbishop of Mexico
      - 55, Copy of a royal cedula to the archbishops and bishops and other archdiocesan and diocesan officials of the islands and mainland of the Ocean Sea. Toledo, August 27, 1560. Also, copy of the response of the archdiocesan authorities of Mexico to the cedula
      - 56, Copy of a royal cedula to the archbishop and bishops of the Spanish Indies
      - 57, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 58, Royal cedula to [Luis de Velasco], Viceroy of New Spain
      - 59, Royal cedula to [Alonso de Montúfar], archbishop of Mexico
      - 60, Royal cedula to [Alonso de Montúfar], archbishop of Mexico
      - 61, Order to Andrés de Cabrera, notary and receptor of the audiencia
      - 62, Viceregal grant of land to Diego Sánchez
      - 63, Royal cedula for the archbishop and cathedral chapter of Mexico
      - 64, Copy of a royal cedula to the audiencia and treasury officials of New Spain
      - 65, Royal cedula to Alonso de Montúfar, archbishop of Mexico
      - 66, Royal cedula to the archbishops and bishops of the Indies
      - 67, Royal letter to [Alonso de Montúfar], archbishop of Mexico
      - 68, Royal cedula to the archbishop and cathedral chapter of Mexico
      - 69, Royal cedula to the archbishop and bishops of the Indies
      - 70, Copy of a royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 71, Copy of a section of a royal document
      - 72, Royal cedula to the archbishop of Mexico
      - 73, Royal cedula to the archbishop of Mexico
      - 74, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 75, Copy of a royal cedula to Martín Enríquez, Viceroy of New Spain, or to his substitute in the governorship
      - 76, Copy of a royal cedula to Martín Enríquez, Viceroy of New Spain, or to his substitute in his absence
      - 77, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 78, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 79, Royal cedula to Martín Enríquez, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 80, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 81, Royal letter to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 82, Royal cedula to the audiencia of New Spain
      - 83, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 84, Royal letter to [Diego Romano], bishop of Tlaxcala
      - 85, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 86, Copy of a royal cedula to the cathedral chapter of Mexico
      - 87, Copy of a royal cedula to the royal treasury officials of New Spain
      - 88, Copy of a royal cedula to Martín Enríquez, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 89, Royal letter to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 90, Royal letter to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 91, Copy of a royal cedula to Martín Enríquez, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 92, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 93, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 94, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 95, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 96, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 97, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 98, Copy of a royal letter to Pedro Moya de Contreras, archbishop of Mexico
      - 99, Copy of a royal cedula to the audiencia of La Plata de los Charcas, Upper Peru
      - 100, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 101, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 102, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico
      - 103, Royal cedula to [Pedro Moya de Contreras], archbishop of Mexico and to the vicar-general and the oldest canon or dignitary
      - 104, Viceregal order
      - 105, Royal cedula to the archbishop of Mexico
      - 106, Royal license
      - 107, Royal cedula to [García Guerra], archbishop of Mexico
      - 108, Royal cedula to [Juan de Mañosca], archbishop of Mexico or, if the see is vacant, to the cathedral chapter
      - 109, Royal cedula to the Count of Alva de Aliste y Villaflor, Viceroy of New Spain (or to the person or persons who might be in charge of the government)
      - 110, Royal letter to the Count of Alva de Aliste de Villaflor, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 111, Royal cedula to the Count of Alva de Aliste, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 112, Royal letter to the Count of Alva de Aliste, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 113, Royal cedula to the Count Alva de Aliste, Viceroy of New Spain (or to the person or persons who have charge of the government of New Spain)
      - 114, Royal cedula to the Count of Alva de Aliste, Viceroy of New Spain
      - 115, Royal cedula to [Mateo Saga de Bugueira], archbishop of Mexico
      - 116, Royal order for the archbishops and bishops of the Spanish New World
    - 117, Alvarado Tezozómoc, Fernando, chronicle of Mexico, circa 1600
      - 117, La corónica Mexicana
    - 118, Vespucci, Amerigo, Copybook containing an anthology of miscellaneous material including copies of letters from Vespucci to Lorenzo de' Medici and an unknown correspondent, 1500-circa 1503, circa 1547-circa 1574, undated
      - 118/1, Anotazione de certi particolari tratti dalle stori[e] del guicardine
      - 118/2, Lettere di Amerigo Vespucci. [Copy of a letter to Lorenzo di Pier Francesco de' Medici]
      - 118/3, Copia d'una parte d una lettera d'Amerigo Vespucci
      - 118/4, Tratto da Lucio Anneo senacha: sopra lira
      - 118/5, Tratto dalla storia Ecresiastica [sic] Di Euxibio cexariense
      - 118/6, Dechiarazione di molti bedetti et uocaboli sopra lopera del furioso di L[udovi]co ariosto
      - 118/7, Somario Di Guerre civile de romani Tratti da Appiano Alex[andri]no
      - 118/8, Notes on Florentine history taken from Guicciardini's La Historia di Italia
    - 119, Vespucci, Amerigo, Soderini, Piero, letter, 1504, 1802
      - 119/1, Letter[a] de Americo. Vespucci. pro viagio a chalicut. [Copy of letter to Piero Soderini, Gonfaloniere of the Republic of Florence.]
      - 119/2, Varianti tratte da un Codice posseduto dal P. Antonio Amoretti d'Oneglia della Congreg[azion]e della Madre di Dio
    - 120, Vázquez de Tapia, Bernardino, narrative of merits and services, circa 1544, circa 1630 (Box 2, Reel 1)
      - 120, Copy of a narrative of merits and services [to Antonio de Mendoza, Viceroy of New Spain. Mexico, circa 1544 ]
    - 121, Verrazzano, Giovanni da, and family, letters, documents, and transcripts, 1433-1768, undated, (2 folders)
      - 121, Collection of letters, documents, and transcripts relating to Giovanni da Verrazzano and the Verrazzano family
    - 122, Núñez Cabeza de Vaca, Alvar, 1512, 1530, 1557
      - 122/1, Deed of sale of land to Bartolomé Dávila
      - 122/2, Receipt to the jurado Juan de Cabra for moneys paid
      - 122/3, Settlement of a lien on property of Hernando Morales
    - 123-139, Decrees, letters, instructions, reports, and other documents concerning legislation for Spanish America, 1526-1567 (Box 2, Reel 1)
      - 123, Letter to the president and oidores of the Council of the Indies
      - 124, Royal letter to the president and members of the Council of the Indies
      - 125, Opinion addressed to His Imperial Majesty
      - 126, Statement of opinion
      - 127, Opinion addressed to His Imperial Majesty
      - 128, Opinion addressed to His Imperial Majesty
      - 129, Opinion presented to [Cardinal Loaysa, president of the Junta of Valladolid]
      - 130, Opinion addressed to His Imperial Majesty
      - 131, Capitulos tractados entre la ciudad de Mex[i]co y El marq[ue]s de Falces Virrey sobre el assiento de las Cortes y perpetuydad de la tierra
      - 132, Opinion addressed to His Majesty (Box 3, Reel 1)
      - 133, Letter to His Royal Majesty
      - 134, Statement of opinion
      - 135, Opinion addressed to His Imperial Majesty
      - 136, El Pareçer que los ofiçiales de su mag[es]t[ad] desta nueva españa dan a lo que su mag[es]t[ad] sezaria manda çerca de la perpetuydad de los yndios y pueblos desta nueva españa
      - 137, Opinion addressed to His Imperial Majesty
      - 138, El parecer de los q[ue] se han juntado por mandado de v[uestra] m[ages]t[ad] a entender en las cosas de las Yndias despues de hayer oydo al padre fray b[a]r[tolo]me de las casas y fray Jacobo de tastera y el licenciado Salmeron asy de palabra como por escripto
      - 139, Petitions to His Imperial Majesty
      - Miscellany, 1877, undated
    - 140, Velasco, Luis de, and Antonio de Mendoza, viceregal order book, 1548-1552 (Box 4, Reel 2)
      - 140, Viceregal orderbook
    - Ursúa, Pedro de, and Lope de Aguirre expedition (Box 5, Reel 2)
      - 141, Ipori, Gerónimo de, report, circa 1580-1600
        - 141, Del Río Marañon y de su descubrimi[ent]o y sus nazimi[ent]os y de otras muchas particularidades del, y de la Jornada q[ue] hizo P[edr]o de orsua
      - 142, Unknown narrative, circa 1561-1600
        - 142, Relazion De todo lo suçedido En la Jornada de omagua que por otro nombre es el dorado desde que fue encargada a Pedro de Orsua Por el marques de canete... y de como el cruel Tirano Lope de Aguirre llegó a las isla [sic] de la margarita y de las crueldadades q[ue] Hizo hasta salir de la d[ic]ha ysla ...
      - 143, Philip II, King of Spain, copy of royal dispatch, 1550, 1562
        - 143, Copy of a royal cedula to the audiencia of Los Reyes [Lima], Peru. Madrid, October 3, 1562. With an appended list of those involved in the Lope de Aguirre revolt and a paragraph of a royal letter to Pedro de la Gasca
    - 144, Gourgues, Dominique de, and family, 1558-1593, 1838-1866, undated
      - 144/1, Power of attorney
      - 144/2, Power of attorney
      - 144/3, Document
      - 144/4, Domingue de Gourgue
      - 144/5, Power of attorney to Raymond Blizeau
      - 144/6, Settlement of accounts
      - 144/7, Receipt